# 广西·桂林
Guilin, Guangxi
# 走了 吃米粉去了
Let's go, time to eat rice vermicelli
# 哦 这边一两是4块钱 二两是5块钱
Oh, over here 1 liang is 4 yuan, 2 liang is 5 yuan
# 咱们要一个二两的（米粉）
We want a 2 liang order (of vermicelli)
# 你好 我要一个二两的
Hello, I want a 2 liang order
# 我们前面差不多有10个人
There are about 10 people ahead of us
# 应该不会排太久
Shouldn't be long
# 我的两个 不要蒜
I have 2 orders, no garlic
# 什么东西
What
# 她说不要蒜
She said no garlic
# 蒜要说 才加的
Have to ask for garlic before we add it
# 不说 不帮你放的
Don't say anything we won't add
# 米粉
Rice vermicelli
# 锅烧
Braised pork
# 牛肉
Beef
# 花生
Peanuts
# 一般会放四五片的牛肉 四五片的锅烧
Normally you get 4-5 slices of beef, 4-5 slices of guo shao (braised pork)
# 加点酸笋
Add some sour bamboo shoots
# 酸豆角
Sour string beans
# 香葱
Spring onions
# 多放点香葱
Add some more spring onions
# 这边还有青红辣椒
Over here there's also green/red chili peppers
# 最后就是干辣椒
Finally, the dried chili pepper
# 这个就是5块钱的卤菜米粉
This is thus the 5 yuan rice vermicelli with braised meat.
# 它里面是没有菜的 只有卤味
It doesn't have any veggies inside, just the braised meat
# 而且是加了差不多五片吧 五片的牛肉
And there's about 5 slices, 5 slices of beef
# 还有五片的锅烧
And 5 slices of guo shao
# 它这个米粉类似于干拌的
The vermicelli is similar to the dry-stirred dish
# 只是浇了一勺的卤汁
Just it has about a spoonful of the braising sauce
# 而且舀卤汁的木桶很小
The spoon is very small
# 只有那么一小勺
Just that little spoonful
# 咱们后来还放了酸豆角 干辣椒这些
We then added sour string brings, dried peppers etc
# 要把它拌一下
Gotta mix it a bit
# 肉还是不少的
There's a decent amount of meat
# 米粉很爽滑
The vermicelili is pretty slick
# 但是里面的汤汁是咸辣 咸辣的
But the soup inside is salty-spicy, salty-spicy
# 米粉吃起来虽然说是 弹牙 爽滑
Eating the vermicelli has an al dente but slick mouthfeel
# 但是细嚼起来 还有这种糯糯的口感
But on smaller bites there's a slight softening mouthfeel
# 不紧实
(Loose noodles)
But on smaller bites there's a slight softening mouthfeel
# 咱们在里面还加了一些酸豆角
We also added these sour string beans
# （还有酸笋）
# 真是酸豆角 伴着酸辣的味道
(and also sour bamboo shoots)
Really is the sour string beans, mixed with the sour-spicy taste
# 因为它的卤汁有点香辣的味道
Because the braising sauce has some savory spicy flavor
# 还有这个辣椒
And this chili pepper
# 几者融合在一起
The melding of all these
# 真的是 太妙了
Really, it's too perfect
# 这碗粉 有肉 有粉 只卖5块钱
This bowl of vermicelli, has meat, vermicelli, and costs only 5 yuan
# 而且是这么大的量
And it's such a large amount
# 真的是在桂林吃米粉 太幸福了
Justifiably, in Guilin eating vermicelli, life is too good
# 真是下面的料也不想让它浪费
Don't want to waste the ingredients on the bottom either
# 所以说 就不停地用米粉去拌调料汁
So that's why you keep stirring the braising sauce with the vermicelli
# 虽然说它很少 但是拌一拌 总还是有的
Though there's not that much, but once you stir it up there's still some (of the braising sauce).
# 有了卤汁 即使是没有肉 你也可以干吃一碗
With the braising sauce, even though you don't have any meat, you can still eat a bowl (of just vermicelli)
# 真的是这碗粉的灵魂
It really is the soul of this bowl of vermicelli
# 辣椒真的很辣
The chili pepper is very spicy
# 吃到下面还有肉
There's more meat at the bottom
# 它这个锅烧是脆皮猪肉
This guo shao is a crispy skin coated pork
# （外面炸的金黄 吃起来嘎嘣脆 里面肥肉多些）
# 放在里面 其实能增加香味
(Deep fried, golden brown, crispy, with more fat inside)
Added in, can add to the umami
# 刚才点餐的时候 本来想再多加点锅烧
While I was ordering, I had thought about adding more guo shao
# （5块钱可以多加一份）
# 没有吃过
(5 yuan for an extra order)
Never had it before
# 但是点餐的大哥说 不要多加了
But the host said don't add any more
# 因为最近锅烧比较紧俏
Because guo shao is a bit hard to get lately
# 5元的粉里的锅烧已经够吃了
5 yuan's worth of vermicelli guo shao should be enough
# 剩下的锅烧还是留给更多的人吧
Leave some guo shao for other people
# 我还要说一点就是
Another point I want to add
# 它这边是可以加蒜的
You can add garlic here
# 如果说 你说了 要吃蒜
If you tell them you want to eat garlic
# 阿姨会拿一个蒜瓣放在案板上
The lady will take a piece of garlic, place it on the cutting board
# 然后用刀背拍一下 放在碗里
Use the cleaver to smack it, then put it in the bowl
# 但是如果不说 是不加蒜的
But if you don't say anything, they won't add garlic
# 它这边就是4元一两尝尝味
Over here it's 4 yuan for 1 liang, for a sampler
# 5元二两能够吃饱
5 yuan for 2 liang to fill you up
# 再大的饭量 6块钱三两也能够吃撑
even larger, 6 yuan 3 liang, eat until you're very full
# 而且这边的酸豆角 辣椒随便加
Also the sour string beans, peppers, add as much as you want
# 就是这么实惠
It's very price affordable
# 这边的桌子其实是有限的
There are a limited number of tables
# 很多人来吃饭
Lots of people come to eat
# 找不到桌子 甚至说拼不上桌 怎么办
If you can't get a table, or can't even share a table with someone, what can you do
# 就是拿着米粉 站在吃
Take the vermicelli bowl and eat it while standing
# 而且大家吃米粉的速度很快
Everyone eats vermicelli very quickly
# 几分钟就可以吃完
Done in a few minutes
# 也能够发现 我后面的人 很多都是站着吃了
You can tell, behind me a lot of people are eating it while standing
# 咱们喝汤呢 就跑外面来喝了
We decided to come outside to drink the (remainder of) the soup
# 给别的人也让个座
Give our seats to someone else
# 哇
Wow
# 我不得不感叹　这边的水真的是太清了
I have to say, the water here is so clear
# 站在岸上　都能够看到海草
Even standing on the pier, you can see the seagrasses
# 像一棵海草　海草　海草随风飘摇
Like a sea grass, sea grass, sea grass, swaying with the wind
# 关 注
# 雪 鱼 探 店
Please subscribe to Xue Yu